<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter writ to an atheistical acquaintance upon his turning papist in his old age by a person of honour.</title>
            <author>Shannon, Francis Boyle, Viscount, 1623-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38232</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17215696</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17215696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59540)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1100:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter writ to an atheistical acquaintance upon his turning papist in his old age by a person of honour.</title>
                  <author>Shannon, Francis Boyle, Viscount, 1623-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Shannon by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106263:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106263:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER WRIT TO AN Atheiſtical Acquaintance UPON <hi>His turning Papiſt</hi> IN HIS OLD AGE.</p>
            <p>By a Perſon of HONOUR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Taylor,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106263:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106263:2"/>
            <head>A Letter, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>'TWAS the ſaying of a great Prelate, <hi>That a Man of no Religion, might eaſily be of any;</hi> and tho' I remember your ill Living, and this Biſhop's true ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet I could not but be ſurprized at the News of your turning Papiſt, eſpecially conſidering you had attain'd, not only to the full Years of Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the Old Age of Experience, which ſtill is, or ever ought to be, the Parent of Wiſdom and Conſideration, both great Enemies to Popery.</p>
            <p>But upon more ſerious Thoughts, I find Old Age to be the fitteſt Seaſon of a Man's whole Life to turn Papiſt in, becauſe 'tis neareſt to that of Dotage; and ſince you are upon loſing your Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (as I conclude you are by turning Papiſt) I can aſſure you, you could not have pick'd out a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſo fit for one that has loſt his Senſes, as that of the Roman Church, becauſe you muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be out of them, before you can be admitted into it, ſince none can be a thorow pac'd Papiſt, who does not believe the Doctrin of Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and none can believe that Doctrin, who does believe his own Senſes, ſince if you credit them, you cannot believe it; a ſtrange Article of Religion where to urge the Teſtimony of Senſe is an Offence, and to produce the Arguments of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106263:3"/>is no leſs than High Treaſon againſt the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Dignity of this Majeſtick Popiſh Miracle, call'd Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>But ſince I remember you never before own'd your ſelf to be of any Religion, (ſtill living as if you had none;) I cannot ſay you have now chang'd your Religion, but choſen it, and indeed conſidering how many Years of Deliberation you took before you did it; in my Opinion after all, you have cull'd out the very pooreſt of all the Flock; for <hi>Amſterdam</hi> could not have given you a worſe, I mean as to the true Direction of your Soul to Heaven; nor yet a better to convey it thither, if you will believe your Prieſt's falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Salvation; for if you have much Mony, no matter how little Religion; ſince you may with it purchaſe a whole Bundle of Abſolutions and Indulgencies ſufficient to keep your Soul out of Purgatory, which is the Parent of Indulgencies invented by the Roman Church, meerly to fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and cozen the Rich out of their Eſtates.</p>
            <p>And tho' our bleſſed Saviour bid the young Man in the Goſpel, who had great Poſſeſſions, <hi>To ſell all and give to the Poor and follow him, (for 'tis as hard for a Rich Man to enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, as 'tis for a Camel to paſs through the Eye of a Needle,)</hi> yet the Popiſh Clergy will not allow the Rich to ſell any thing, but they muſt convey all they have to the Patrimony of the Church, and then they ſhall be ſure to purchaſe Heaven for their Mony; for, as the Roman Church can by their Miraculous Art, Tranſubſtantiate a ſmall Piece of Wafer into the full bulk of a Man's Body; ſo they can with the ſame Eaſe, and by the ſame Art, Tranſubſtantiate and ſtretch the ſmall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106263:3"/>Eye of a Needle, to the large Size of a Door, wide enough to let you into Paradice without ſtooping, though you were as big as a Camel; for they will tell you, St. <hi>Peter</hi> left with them the Keys of Heaven, and they have Power to keep out and let in whom they pleaſe; ſo that if you can but pay your Prieſt Mony enough on Earth, he will never fail to promiſe you a good purchaſe in Heaven; for he is ſo good a Chriſtian, that he will give you Heavenly Treaſure for your Earthly, by Bill of Exchange on the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> upon the Credit of ſo many Maſſes he will make to her, for your Soul on Earth; but be not deceived by them, as you muſt certainly be if you rely on them.</p>
            <p>For this falſe pretended Heavenly Wealth he tells you he'll furniſh you with, is but meer fairy Treaſure, which only laſts till it be diſcover'd, and then vaniſheth aſſoon as
'tis; it being not more againſt the Courſe of Nature, that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny you pay for thoſe Maſſes ſhould aſcend to Heaven, than 'tis againſt the Stream of Reaſon to believe, that they ſhould carry your Soul there; ſuch common Sail-Maſſes for the Souls of the Dead, being but like fine bright Clouds in the Sky, which tho' they look high, and make a great ſhew, yet they have no real Subſtance, being but meer Airy Apparitions,</p>
            <p>Therefore, tho' I was ever an Enemy to your Religion, yet I am ſtill ſo much a Friend to your Perſon, as to wiſh, that as you have had always a great ſhare of natural Wit, ſo you may now have ſo much Heavenly Wiſdom, as to pray to God to open your Eyes before Death quite clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them, that you may through his Grace clearly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106263:4"/>ſee the foppiſh Religion you have now choſen, and the ungodly Life you have ſtill led, and that you may ſeriouſly reflect and truly repent of both, and often remember that Death will ſoon ſeize you, and Judgment will ſoon follow it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray to God for your own Soul, whilſt you are in this World, and truſt not to the Mony you leave with your Prieſt to pray for it after you are gone to the next, for then ſuch Maſſes can only cheat you of your Mony, but can never rid you of your Sins.</p>
            <p>And did I not certainly know that you had much rather (in Point of Religion) read a dull Lay-man's Letter, than a Learned Divines Book; not that you can be ignorant, but that ſuch a good Book muſt be much better for your uſe, than ſuch a ſhort Letter; but becauſe this Letter, is ſo much ſhorter than ſuch a good Book, and conſequently leſs troubleſome to read, for all Troubles you eſteem Evils, and of Evils the leaſt is beſt, or rather leſs ill; And therefore had I not known this ſort of Logick to ſuit exactly with your lazy and unzea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Humour, I ſhould have rather recommended to your reading, a Sermon writ by that Pious and Learned Divine Dr. <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> for many Writers do but in a manner fence with their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt Popery, but this Dr. makes all his home thruſts, and wounds the Papiſt in the very Vitals of their Religion; and as a skilful Painter may draw exactly well a great Beauty in ſmall Proportions, ſo this Learned Perſon has largely confuted Popery in one ſhort Sermon.</p>
            <p>And as none can be ſaid to ſteal from the Bible, tho' he takes and quotes never ſo many Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes out of it. So none can be juſtly accuſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106263:4"/>for having ſtoln or plunder'd this Reverend Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of any of his Arguments againſt the common Enemy the Papiſts, becauſe he deſign'd them freely for the benefit of all ſuch, as will employ all or any of them, to that uſe, they being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd by him, on that publick and charitable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, as the Lands they call Commons, are left to certain Pariſhes, who are never to be fenced in for private uſe, but ſtill left open for publick Benefit.</p>
            <p>Nor did I ever hear of any Man that valued Mony the leſs, becauſe it paſſed thorow many hands before it came to his, nor a good Receipt the worſe, becauſe 'twas given him by another, and not found out by himſelf; and therefore, ſince you now find your ſelf infected with a foul malignant Inclination to Popery, and ſince I can here give you a Sovereign Medicine againſt it; never trouble your ſelf to examin who found it out, where the Drugs grew, or from whence they came, or from whom I had them, ſo they can cure you. And this I am ſure I can truly ſay, That what I have taken out of Doctor <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Sermon, was not to ſhew my own good read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but to ſet out your bad Religion, which is chiefly made up of Ceremony and Shew.</p>
            <p>But the Papiſt bids the Proteſtant Hereticks hold their prating, for they have an Argument and a Queſtio, that's able to knock them all in the Head, (ſure they mean only ſuch a have no Brains in them.) Their Argument is as very common, as 'tis highly irrational, which is this; The Proteſtant Church holds a Papiſt may be ſaved, the Roman Church denies that a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant can, therefore 'tis wiſer and more ſafe to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106263:5"/>of that Church, to which Salvation is granted on both ſides: But this is a weak ſophiſtical kind of reaſoning, and only fit to take ſuch as have no Reaſon; for by this Argument the then Donatiſts that held the Baptiſm of the Catholicks was not good, and the Catholicks that held the Baptiſm of the Donatiſts was good ſhou'd make it reaſonable to infer, that therefore St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and the other Catholicks ought according to this Rule, to have gon and been re baptized by the Donatiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both ſides acknowledged their Baptiſm to be good.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo owned a Poſſibility of Salvation, tho' with great Difficulty to thoſe, who built with Straw and Stubble on the Fouudation of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that is, who built upon the Jewiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and Obſervances, but they denied a Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Salvation to St. <hi>Paul</hi> and his Followers, ſaying, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs they were circumciſed and kept the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>they could not be ſaved;</hi> ſo that by this worthy Argument, St. <hi>Paul</hi> and his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ought to have gon over to thoſe Judaizing Chriſtians, becauſe it was acknowledged by both ſides, that they might be ſaved; but St. <hi>Paul</hi> was too wiſe, to leave a certain way of Salvation, only for a meer Poſſibility of being ſaved.</p>
            <p>Their Queſtion is a Twin-Brother in Ignorance to this their Argument; for the Papiſts ask the Proteſtants, Where was their Church before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> who anſwer, Where their Church was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> in the Bible, where I am ſure the Papiſt will find none of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils Twelve New Articles of Faith recorded; as being never taught by our Bleſſed Saviour, or ever ſo much as mentioned by any of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106263:5"/>in any of their Epiſtles or Writings; and yet forſooth, theſe are the Old Apoſtolical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins, which <hi>(none who does not believe) can be ſaved;</hi> yet I ſhall beg your Patience to give me leave to name and look a little into ſome of theſe new <hi>Trent</hi> Articles of Faith.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſhall be on that Unchriſtian Doctrin, (as Doctor <hi>Tillotſon</hi> juſtly ſtiles it) called Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation; and the reaſon the Reverend Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor names it Unchriſtian is, becauſe 'tis a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin that undermines the very Foundation of Chriſtianity, as will plainly appear (ſays he) if we but conſider the grand Argument, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles uſed to convince the World of the Truth of Chriſtianity, and that was this, That our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, the Author of this Doctrin, wrought ſuch and ſuch Miracles, and appeared to them, and converſed with them after his Death, which they confirm by an Infallible Teſtimony, (which the Papiſt will not allow as ſuch, becauſe they will believe no Infallibility out of their own Church;) That they themſelves were Eye witneſſes, both to his Miracles and Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>So that 'tis abſolutely neceſſary to rely on the Teſtimony of the Senſes; for if the Apoſtles Eyes had failed them, then they were not ſure they ſaw his Miracles, or himſelf after his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then the main Aſſurance of Chriſt's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riſen falls to the Ground, and all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctrin was buried with him in his Grave; for if there be no aſſurance in the Teſtimony of the Senſes, there's no Aſſurance of Chriſtianity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no aſſurance of Chriſt's being riſen from the Dead; ſo that the Buiſineſs is brought to this fair Iſſue, If the Teſtimony of the Senſes are to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106263:6"/>be truſted, then Tranſubſtantiation is falſe, and if they are not to be truſted, then no man can ſay that Chriſtian Religion is true; for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſeeing Chriſt after his Reſurrection, is the great proof we have that he is riſen.</p>
            <p>Farther granting the Scripture to be a Divine Revelation, and that theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> muſt be neceſſarily taken in a ſtrict literal Senſe, I ask the Papiſt, What greater Evidence has any Man, that theſe words are in the Bible, than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man has that the Bread is not changed in the Sacrament? Nay none has ſo much, for we have only the Evidence of one Senſe, that theſe words are in the Bible, but that the Bread is not changed into the Body of Chriſt, we have the concurring Teſtimony of ſeveral of the Senſes together.</p>
            <p>How erroneous then muſt the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be in this point, that holds it to be a principal Article of the Chriſtian Faith, and ſo preached by the Apoſtles, by which they throw a great Contradiction and Abſurdity on their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, that they ſhould give for the great proof of the Truth of Chriſtianity, That the Senſes are to be truſted, and at the ſame time give it for one of the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, that the Senſes are not to be truſted, as the Apoſtles muſt do, if they did Preach the Doctrin of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, which is an utter denying that the Teſtimony of the Senſes are to be relied on.</p>
            <p>In a word, if it once be admitted, that the Senſes of all Men may be deceived in the moſt plain and ſenſible Matters that can be, (for there can be no greater difference, than between a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bit of a Wafer, and the whole Body of a Man,) there's no way left to convey or prove a Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106263:6"/>
            <p>But the Papiſt in anſwer to this, ask's us, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God cannot impoſe upon the Senſes of Men, and repreſent to them things otherwiſe than they are? Yes ſurely, if he has revealed that he wou'd, we are undoubtedly to believe him; but then we ought to be aſſured that he hath made ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, which aſſurance no Man can have, the certainty of Senſe being taken away.</p>
            <p>But to ſhew you that this Doctrin of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation is far from being Apoſtolical; it was brought into the Roman Church by the Lateran Council, under Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, and with it that Reverend Doctrin of depoſing Kings in caſe of Hereſie, and abſolving their Subjects from their Allegiance; Theſe are two Twin-Doctrins that hunted in Couples; and for the laſt, tho' they are now aſham'd to own it, yet the Popes were not formerly ſhy to practiſe it.</p>
            <p>Next their worſhipping of Images, which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, notwithſtanding all their ſubtle Diſtinctions and Evaſions about it, is but the very ſame the Heathens us'd in the ſame Caſe, and is as point blank againſt the Second Commandment, as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Murther is againſt the Sixth, which the Popiſh Teachers are ſo ſenſible of, and ſo afraid the People ſhould be ſo too, that therefore in their ordinary Catechiſms, and Manuals of Devotion, they leave out the Second Commandment, and divide the Tenth into two to make up the Number; That the Infallible Church of <hi>Rome</hi> might not appear ſo fallible as to act ſo contrary to the Commands of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſs by their taking away the Cup in the Sacrament from the Laity, tho' our Saviour orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to be given in both kinds; and they might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106263:7"/>as well take away the Bread, as the Cup, and both as either.</p>
            <p>And for the Papiſts praying in an unknown Tongue; do but read St. <hi>Paul</hi> on that Subject as to the great Errour of doing it, and he will ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you, tho' he cannot convince them.</p>
            <p>Next let us refiect a little upon that part of the Romiſh Doctrin of praying to, and worſhipping of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which hath been now for ſome Ages paſt, a principal Part of their Religion; for they build Chappels, erect Altars, and ſanctify Holy-days to her; in ſhort, ſhe makes the greateſt Part, both of their Publick Worſhip and private Devotions, they praying to her more than either to God, or our Saviour, the Papiſt uſing ten <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> for one <hi>Pater Noſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed one who conſiders this, and had never read the Bible, might well have concluded, that there had been more ſaid of her in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, than of God, or Chriſt; and that it had been full from one End to the other of Precepts and Exhortations, for the worſhipping of her; yet I defy any Papiſt to ſhew me (as to this Doctrin of praying to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi>) where ſhe's ſo much as once named by the Apoſtles in any of their Epiſtles; or where there's one Verſe in the whole Bible, that ſavours in the leaſt of paying Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to her, but rather the contrary, our Saviour ſeeming to take all Occaſions to reſtrain us from it, as when they told him, <hi>Your Mother and your Brethren are without, who, ſays he, are my Mother and my Brethren? he that doth the Will of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſame is my Mother, my Siſter, and my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And when the Woman broke out in a Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, concerning the bleſſed Mother of the Lord,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106263:7"/>bleſſed is the Womb that bare thee, and the Paps that gave thee ſuck, our Saviour diverts it to another thing, by ſaying, <hi>Yea rather bleſſed are they that hear the word of God and keep it;</hi> does our Saviour, or his Apoſtles in any of their particular Directions and Precepts concerning Prayer, and the Manner of it, and by whom we are to addreſs our ſelves to God, give the leaſt hint, or intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of praying to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or making uſe of her Mediation for us? or is there one Verſe in the whole Bible, that orders us in the leaſt to pay her Worſhip?</p>
            <p>In ſhort, did God ever command it? did ever our Saviour teach it? did ever the Apoſtles Preach it? or did ever the Primitive Chriſtians practiſe it? Nay, did any of the Writers of the firſt three hundred Years, ever name any ſuch thing as pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Worſhip, or making her any part of their Religion? Indeed about the middle of the fourth Century it begun to creep in among ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Perſons; and therefore <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> who lived about that time, call'd it the Hereſie of Women.</p>
            <p>And ſince 'tis ſo much taught, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly practiſed in the Roman Church, without the leaſt Colour of a Command in God's Word for it; give me leave a little to reflect on the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility that the Roman Church pretends to; becauſe I am ſure, this is a Doctrin that's able to bring into her as many Errours as ſhe thinks convenient to receive, (which is more than a few,) and yet this infallible Church cannot yet tell where this Infallibility is ſeated, whether in the Pope alone, or in a Council alone, or in both together, or in a diffuſive Body of Chriſtians,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106263:8"/>but they are ſure they have it, tho' they know not where it is.</p>
            <p>Indeed I can't imagin, how they, or any can think it reaſonable, that this Infallibility was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed on the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that all the primitive Chriſtians did believe it, and had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to it, and yet that this very Roman Church ſhould be ſtill at a loſs where 'tis, and that ſhould make a difference, which ſhould be the End of all Differences. That not one word ſhould be intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all the Bible of this high and peculiar Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge above all other Churches, and that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in all their Epiſtles, ſhould give no notice or caution to Chriſtians, to appeal to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for determining any Difficulties, which even in thoſe Times hapned among them, and that they ſhould then never ſpeak of it, tho' there were ſo many occaſions for it. Nor that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers in all their Diſputes with the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, ſhould never appeal to this Judge; nay, that they ſhould not do it in all Caſes of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, it being ſuch a ſure and ſpeedy way of ending them all among Chriſtians. And ſo I have done with Doctor <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Arguments, and
'twere well for the Papiſt he had done with their Religion too; for his Reaſonings and Arguments like skrew'd Guns, they carry farther, and pierce deeper than any others which are of the ordinary level among us.</p>
            <p>And now by this Infallible Churches leave, tho' I pretend not in the leaſt to be a Scholar, much leſs a Divine, yet I doubt not without being either, to prove the Roman Church, ſince her adding twelve New Articles of Faith to the Old Apoſtolical Creed, which were coyn'd in the Mint of <hi>Trent,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106263:8"/>by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, to be very falſe, and erroneous in her Principles, tho' ſhe does with ſo much Confidence, but no Truth, ſay, that ſhe holds at this time the old, true, Catholick and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Faith, and yet declares her ſelf to believe at the ſame time, the new <hi>Trent</hi> Creed to be the true Catholick Faith, without which no Man can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; which are the very words in that Creed.</p>
            <p>But before I make any farther Progreſs on this Subject, I will recommend to you two Remarks well worth your Obſervation on this worthy Council; The firſt is its heedleſs contradicting and forſwearing in the very firſt Article: The ſecond is the want of Chriſtian Charity, by damning all the Churches before <hi>Trent</hi> Council; Two foul Crimes very unbecoming a General Council, whoſe buſineſs is not to perform, but reform Sin. Now you muſt firſt know, that the Obſervance of the twelve <hi>Trent</hi> Articles of Faith, are bound upon all by Oath, and in the very firſt Article they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to embrace the Apoſtolical and Eccleſiaſtical Tradition, and yet at the very ſame time ſwear to obſerve all that's decreed by that Council, which orders that the Holy Communion ſhall be adminiſtred to the Laity but in one kind, when for above a thouſand Years after Chriſt, it was given to them in both, in all the Chriſtian Churches over the whole World; and the Roman Church cannot deny, but that it was our Saviour's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as well as all the Churches practice, for ſo many years; Nay, in the fourth Article of the <hi>Trent</hi> Creed, they uſe theſe very words; That they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and approve the Rites of the Catholick Church, in the ſolemn Adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; and yet tho' the receiving it in both
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106263:9"/>kinds, is both Apoſtolical Tradition and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actical Practice, yet they poſitively forbid it to the Laity: The Concluſion makes it ſelf.</p>
            <p>My ſecond Obſervation is, how uncharitable this Council is, and all its Diſciples in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning all other Churches; for ſurely, theſe <hi>Trent</hi> Creed-makers have not ſo much Impudence, (tho' I know they have a great deal) as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to follow our Bleſſed Saviour's charitable Doctrin, who commands us to pray for our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; but this worthy Council is ſo very far from praying for their Enemies, as they damn their very Friends, the old Roman Church, with all the Chriſtian Churches diſperſed over the Face of the whole Earth; for ſhe no more than the reſt, did ever hear before the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> that its twelve New Articles, was the old true Catholick and Apoſtolical Faith, without which no Man can be ſaved; all I ſhall ſay to this is, that as Charity covers many Faults, ſo the want of it diſcovers many Vices, which is apparent in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> more than all, becauſe ſhe ſhews leſs Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than any.</p>
            <p>My next buſineſs is to ſhew you, that from the days of the Apoſtles, to the Time of the <hi>Trent</hi> Council, among the many Creeds named by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius, Euſebius</hi> and others; none of them ever made the leaſt attempt of altering, or much leſs of adding any one new Article of Faith, but only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd the Old, eſteeming the Apoſtles Creed to be fully ſufficient; being as <hi>Tertullian</hi> elegantly ſtiles it, <hi>A Little Body of great Truths,</hi> The <hi>Rule of Faith,</hi> inſtituted by Chriſt, and tranſmitted from him to his Apoſtles.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106263:9"/>
            <p>I could here for the Confirmation of this Truth, produce you the Teſtimonies of all the Eminent Fathers of all Ages of the Chriſtian Church; but that would not only tire your Patience, but ſwell this Letter above the moderate Bounds of one; to prevent which, I ſhall only quote you ſome few of the many, which will be enough to juſtifie, that all acknowledged this great known Truth; that there was never added any new Article of Faith, to the old Apoſtolical Creed before the <hi>Trent</hi> Council.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I ſhall only here name you the firſt four General Councils, thoſe of <hi>Nice, Conſtantinople, Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon.</hi> And as to the firſt of theſe Councils, when the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers met to ſettle the Controverſie about the Son of God, they were ſo far from making any new Creed, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any New Article to the Old, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded only the meaning of one of the Articles, the Senſe of which the <hi>Arians</hi> had perverted, and had therefore little Deſign of changing or adding to the Chriſtian Faith, contain'd in the Apoſtles Creed, when at their meeting they read no other Creed but it.</p>
            <p>And St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> before he began his Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the firſt Book of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> ſets down what the Catholick Faith is, which he ſays is nothing elſe, but what is contain'd in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed.</p>
            <p>But what need I alledge more than the words of the great <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> on this Subject, in the Letter which he and ſome other Biſhops with him writ to the Emperour <hi>Jovian;</hi> where they tell him, that the Faith profeſſed by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, was the very ſame which was Preach'd from the beginning, and unto which all the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106263:10"/>Churches every where conſented to, whether in <hi>Greece, Africk, Spain, France, Italy, &amp;c.</hi> with all the Churches of the Eaſt, (a few <hi>Arians</hi> excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;) and then ſetting down the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, they conclude, in this Faith 'tis neceſſary for all to remain, as being Divine and Apoſtolical, and therefore not to be changed; which is a moſt plain Declaration, (by the Council of <hi>Trens</hi>'s leave) that the Faith contained in this Creed, is not at all defective and ſhort, as the <hi>Trento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> did believe it was, by their adding more to it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſays, that the true Church through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the World, hath but one and the ſame Faith, ſhe had from the beginning, which I'm ſure plainly concludes, that the now Roman Church cannot be the true Church, becauſe it holds not the ſame Faith now, ſhe did in the beginning, having enlarg'd her Creed by twelve new Articles of Faith, coyn'd in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and never heard of in any Chriſtian Church in the whole World, before that late worthy Council.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond general Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> I ſhall not need name here, ſince it contain'd the ſame of the firſt general Council of <hi>Nice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the third general Council aſſembl'd at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> all the Fathers of it were ſo faſt uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together in this Perſwaſion, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed contain'd all things neceſſary to be believ'd, as that Council decreed, that it ſhould not be lawful for any to write, compoſe, offer, or produce any other Article of Faith, than thoſe defined by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council; and if any were ſo bold as to dare the doing of it, if they were-Lay-men,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106263:10"/>they ſhould be Anathematiz'd, and if they were Clergymen or Biſhops, they ſhould be depoſed; which plainly informs us, what would become of the preſent Pope and his Clergy, if he and they had attempted then, what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to do now, which is to add no leſs than twelve new Articles of Faith, as if the old Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Creed was not ſufficient and compleat enough to make up the new Romiſh Church Faith, without the new <hi>Trent</hi> Addition.</p>
            <p>And for the fourth general Council of <hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> it renewed this Canon of the Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> decreeing in a manner the very ſame words, only with this difference, to Lay-men is added Monks, againſt whom the Synod decreed an <hi>Anathema,</hi> if they pretended to teach any other Faith.</p>
            <p>I could alſo here name the fifth general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil held at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> under the Emperour <hi>Juſtinian;</hi> which Council profeſſed in their third Seſſion, that they embraced the ſame Faith with the four foregoing Councils of <hi>Nice, Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and ſo did all the other general Councils ſing the ſame Note, that no new Article of Faith ſhould be added to the old Apoſtolical Creed. Yet the late pretended general Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> added no leſs than twelve new Articles; which was but a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that they eſteem'd the Apoſtles Creed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective and light by twelve Grains, or elſe ſurely they would never have added that Number to make it weight, as they thought and pretended to do; by which that Council does in effect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves to be more knowing in what is neceſſary to true Faith, than the firſt four
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106263:11"/>General Councils, and the very Holy inſpir'd A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves: And this that Council ſays, (but with great impudence and falſeneſs) is the true old Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith, without which no Man can be ſaved, for 'tis the very words of <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth's Creed.</p>
            <p>This is indeed a princely Doctrin, fit for ſuch a princely Pope, of whom I muſt beg leave, (or elſe I ſhall be ſo bold as to take it) to let ſlip a Leaſe of Popes, and four General Councils againſt his twelve new Articles of Faith.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Pope ſhall be <hi>Pius</hi> the Second, againſt <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth; for this <hi>Pius</hi> the Second con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that before the Time of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, little regard was had of the Roman Church, which is a plain contradiction to Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, and all Popes, ſince that ſhe is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all the Churches; for ſure all the Churches did know the Duty they owed their Mother, ſo well, as not to have neglected the paying it, if they had believ'd it truly due to her; but it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their not paying, they eſteem'd it not truly due.</p>
            <p>My Second Pope is <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, whoſe Character is, That he was the worſt Biſhop that ever went before him, and the beſt that ever came after him; ſure it cannot be upon the Account of upholding, or inlarging the Power of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> for I am very confident, and I believe my Confidence is grounded upon this good Reaſon, that had Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> liv'd in the Time of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, and had been aſſur'd that he had taken upon him to add twelve new Articles to the old Apoſtolical Creed, he would have ſaid the very ſame of him, as he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106263:11"/>did of <hi>John</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> when he was told he had taken upon him, the Title of Univerſal Patriarch or Biſhop; That whoſoever ſhould uſurp to himſelf that Title, was a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of Anti Chriſt: And for his part he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to no other Title, than that of being a Servant to the Servants of God, tho' he was not only then Biſhop of, but Reſident in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> who ſoon after ſucceeded him in the Papacy, tho' he had a leſs humble Chriſtian Mind, yet he had a much higher Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Spirit; for he preſently chang'd that Note, and ſwallowd greedily that ſweet tempting Bit of Univerſal Biſhop, chooſing rather the great Power of being the Head, and Maſter of all the Biſhops on Earth, than the humble Character of being Servant to the Servants of the great God of Heaven. By which he ſhewed the Pride of a bad Pope, but not at all the Humility of a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, by eſteeming the Office of a Pope more perfect freedom, than that of God's Service.</p>
            <p>But this Title of Univerſal Biſhop is attended with ſuch great Dignity, and accompanied with ſuch a large Revenue, that all Pope <hi>Boniface</hi>'s Succeſſors, would never ſince abandon that proud Uſurpation; for tho' the doing it may be a Sin, yet that's nothing to the Pope; for he that has Power to forgive other Mens Sins, may eaſily ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve himſelf of his own; and indeed I believe, he has as full Power to pardon his own Sins, as much as any others.</p>
            <p>But now to return to the Point I was about; this Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> concurr'd in his Opinion with the firſt four General Councils, that no new Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith were to be admitted, but what were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106263:12"/>profeſſed by them: And in his giving an account of his Faith, as the Cuſtom was for every Pope upon the Advancement to his Papal Dignity; he ſpeaks of the firſt four General Councils in ſo high a Stile, as he profeſſed to receive and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them, as the four Books of the Holy Goſpel: How vaſtly differing was the Faith of this Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> from that of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, and the now Roman Church, who, tho' we Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants embrace all the Doctrins of our Saviour contain'd in the Apoſtles Creed, and confirmed by the firſt four General Councils, yet the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will not allow, that the Performance of theſe, with a ſtrict vertuous Life, can afford us ſo much as a Poſſibility of Salvation; To which unchriſtian and uncharitable Doctrin of theirs, I ſhall only anſwer, That the Papiſts by this plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that they forget that Charity is an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Mark of true Chriſtianity; and what the Apoſtle ſaith of particular Chriſtians, is as true of whole Churches, That tho' they have all Faith, yet if they have no Charity, they are nothing.</p>
            <p>The third Pope I ſhall here produce is, <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who being elected to the Papacy, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, if he held the Definitions of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> (which contain'd that of <hi>Nice, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> and the <hi>Epheſine</hi> Creed) To which he made anſwer in a Letter, which is in the Body of the Canon Law, that he received the Definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the firſt four General Councils, concerning the Catholick Faith, and then beginning to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe his Creed, as the faſhion was upon being made Pope; he repeated the Apoſtles Creed, <hi>This is my Faith</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>and the Hope that is in me, by the Gift of God's Mercy, of what St.</hi> Peter <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106263:12"/>us to be ready to anſwer every one, who asketh us a Reaſon, and an Account of it.</hi> Of which I am ſure the <hi>Trentonian</hi> Fathers, with their twelve new additional Articles, can give no good Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count out of Scripture, becauſe there's not a word mention'd of them in it.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſhall conclude with St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Since the Juſt live by Faith, the greater care muſt be taken, that Faith be not corrupted, and then adds, Now the Catholick Faith is made known to the faithful in the Apoſtles Creed; which plainly argues, that ſince the <hi>Trent</hi> Articles are in no part of the Apoſtles Creed, or in God's Word, they can be no part of the Catholick Faith.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude this Point, I ſhall leave it to the Popes for a <hi>Memorandum,</hi> the Example of their Brother Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> who was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by two Councils as an Heretick, and alſo ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Second; And pray, why was this great Scandal and heavy Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment laid upon his Holineſs? the reaſon Pope <hi>Leo</hi> tells us, was, becauſe he conſented to violate the Rule of Apoſtolical Tradition, meaning as it was contain'd in the Apoſtles Creed. And ſurely if declaring a Defect in this Creed be a Violation of it; then certainly nothing can be more plain, than that Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent,</hi> have defiled the Apoſtolical Creed, for they have declared it to be too ſhort and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, by their adding twelve new Articles of Faith to it, ſince 'tis groſs folly to add to a thing, what one believes does not want any Addition.</p>
            <p>And now I have given you a Leaſe of Popes, againſt one Pope, and four General Councils, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106263:13"/>one only pretended one, for I can eſteem that of <hi>Trent</hi> no other, being made up of a Pack of Italian Biſhops, and ſo in effect was no more general, than the ſingle Roman Church is Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and Univerſal, And tho' the Papiſts know, there was a Catholick Church before a Roman; yet they will now include the Catholick in the Roman, and upon that account call themſelves Roman Catholicks, a ſingular Univerſal Church; But Popiſh Bulls are ſo very common in <hi>Rome,</hi> as they are to be the leſs wondred at for it.</p>
            <p>And ſo, I hope, I have ſufficiently prov'd, that this Queſtion of the Papiſt to the Proteſtants is very impertinent, Where was your Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luther?</hi> To which Queſtion we can truly anſwer, (as we did before,) Where I am ſure the Popiſh Creed never was ſince the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> in the Bible. And therefore ſince the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts will attempt caſting Novelty on the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, they ought not to wonder I here ſpeak Truth of theirs: For this their Queſtion to us, will but prove to them, like a Gun very much overcharg'd, which inſtead of hitting the Mark 'tis ſhot at, flies about the Ears of him that ſhoots it. For I can ſafely ſay, becauſe truly, that the preſent Roman Church with her Train of <hi>Trent</hi> Additions, cannot be the ſame true Old Catholick, and Apoſtolical Church, that ſhe was before the Time of that Council, becauſe ſhe has taken a New Creed, and a New Creed muſt make a New Church, as well as a New Faith muſt make a New Religion, and therefore ſhe cannot be altogether the Old Catholick and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Church, ſhe now ſo confidently pretends
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106263:13"/>to, and vainly boaſts of, as being the Miſtreſs and Mother of all Churches, when in truth ſhe's far from being ſo to any one of them; except that of <hi>Trent,</hi> of which we yield her to be the true Mother, as will here appear upon a ſhort Examination into this Matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Roman Church cannot juſtly call her preſent Faith to be altogether Old, becauſe a great part of it is altogether New, as only taking its Date from the Birth of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and all know 'tis not much more than a hundred Years ſince that Council was hatch'd; ſo that the <hi>Trent</hi> Creed, making now a main part of the Romiſh Faith, (which is a Truth the Papiſts dare not deny, without denying a main part of their preſent Faith;) how is it poſſible ſhe can pretend her Faith is altogether Old; when ſhe muſt yield at the ſame Time, that no leſs than twelve Articles of the now Roman Church Faith is in (a manner) altogether New? and how well new Cloth agrees with an Old Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Scripture tells us.</p>
            <p>Nor has the Roman Church any better reaſon for ſtiling her ſelf altogether Catholick, becauſe a main part of the Faith of her Church, is not univerſally believ'd, no not by half the Chriſtian Churches, (I wonder for my part 'tis by any;) ſo that until the Papiſts can make the leſſer part to contain the greater, they muſt not expect to make the Proteſtants believe the ſingle Roman Church, can contain the Catholick, that is, the univerſal Church.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106263:14"/>
            <p>And for the Roman Church ſtiling her ſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Apoſtolical; I cannot at all find ſhe has the leaſt Colour of Reaſon for it, ſince the Date of the <hi>Trent</hi> Creed, which is the preſent Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Faith;) for 'tis moſt certain that Creed was never ſo much as heard of, much leſs taught by any of the Apoſtles, in any of their Epiſtles or Writings, or ever nam'd in any Chriſtian Church over the whole World, for more than fifteen hundred Years after Chriſt; ſo that an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant may as well pretend to be as old as <hi>Methuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> as the New <hi>Trent</hi> Creed can, to be the old Apoſtolical Faith. Therefore to ſum up all in a word, Since the <hi>Trent</hi> Creed makes a main part of the Romiſh Faith, all the Reaſons the Papiſts can give (in my opinion) for their Faith being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Apoſtolical, and their Church the Mother of all Churches, is but that poor weak Womaniſh kind of reaſoning, She is ſo, becauſe ſhe is ſo.</p>
            <p>But for the Proteſtant Religion, I can here eaſily and truly prove it to be altogether Old, altogether Catholick, and altogether Apoſtolical. The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion is truly altogether Old, becauſe we believe the old Apoſtolical Creed, which contains the Doctrins of our Bleſſed Saviour, given by him to his Apoſtles, and confirmed by the firſt four General Councils, which Creed we continue ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt to, without the leaſt taking from it, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to it, which the Papiſts with their additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal New <hi>Trent</hi> Creed, cannot juſtly, nay ſo much as pretend to.</p>
            <p>So that 'tis moſt certain, that unleſs the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts will deny the Apoſtolical Religion to be the Old Religion; they cannot truly ſay, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106263:14"/>is the New. And let the Papiſts but ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly reflect on the <hi>Trent</hi> Creed they believe now, and on that of the firſt four General Councils, which was the Faith, the Romiſh Church held then, and I am ſure, they may as reaſonably attempt to prove a Son may be elder than his natural Father, as to pretend to juſtifie that the <hi>Trent</hi> Creed (of not much more than a hundred Years ſtanding) to be elder than the Apoſtles Creed, which was made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove fifteen hundred Years before it.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſurely the Roman Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or leaſt ought not to deny, that ſince the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Faith is ſtill contain'd intire in the Apoſtles Creed, it muſt be ſo many degrees elder than the Roman Faith, as the Roman Church hath built new Stories, on the old Proteſtant Foundation, ſince at the Time of the firſt four General Councils, (for then Proteſtant and Papiſt were all one Faith;) ſo that if the Roman Church will allow, (what they dare not deny) that their Religion was good at that Time, they cannot juſtly ſay the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants is bad at this Time, ſince we profeſs the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame Creed now, they did then, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church having, (as I ſaid before) not in the leaſt taken from, or added to the Apoſtolical Creed, as I am ſure the Papiſts cannot deny but that they themſelves have: And tho' the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> has caus'd the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to differ much from what ſhe then was; yet praiſed be God, the Proteſtants have not alter'd from what they then were, and therefore we cannot be truly ſaid, to differ more from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> at this Time, than ſhe has differ'd from her ſelf ſince that Time. I mean of the firſt four General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106263:15"/>
            <p>Next I ſay, the Proteſtant Faith is altogether Catholick, becauſe 'twas the Faith, that all the Chriſtian Churches over the whole World profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, (a few <hi>Arians</hi> in the Eaſt only excepted) for above fifteen hundred Years together, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelves can no more juſtly deny, than they can truly prove, that the new Roman Creed, with its <hi>Trent</hi> Addition, was the Faith of all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches in the World, for ſo much as one day, no nor what's worſe, is ever like to be to the laſt day.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, for the Proteſtant Church being now altogether Apoſtolical, the Papiſts may with the ſame reaſon and Juſtice deny the Apoſtles Creed to be Apoſtlical, as to deny our Faith is not ſo, ſince the Proteſtant Faith is contain'd in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, which we never at all varied from, but continued altogether firm to, without the leaſt Alteration or Diminution; a hapyy Truth, which I'm ſure the Roman Church dares not now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, without having no leſs than twelve new Articles of Faith to flie in her Face, and giving her as many Times the Lye for pretending to it.</p>
            <p>And now there remains only to add, That if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has any Inclination to bring the Proteſtant Church into a hearty Unity, and firm Community with her; the beſt and only way will be to take the firſt four General Councils as the Judge and Standard to meaſure all our preſent Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences by, and if the Proteſtants have deviated in the leaſt from them, to reform in what they have differed; and let the Papiſts but do the ſame, and retrench all their idle new ſupernumerary <hi>Trent</hi> Articles of Faith, and disband all their vain ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106263:15"/>Ceremonies, neither of which was ever taught or indeed heard of by the Apoſtles, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, and reduce their Creed to the ſame it was in the Time of the firſt four General Councils, and then the Papiſt as well as Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant will become of the ſame Apoſtolical Faith now, as we were both of us then, that is, be again both of one and the ſame Religion.</p>
            <p>But the Pope's Power is too high, and his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue too great to admit this mortifying Spirit; light Mony can never agree with true Scales, nor Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity like a true Glaſs; no more can the new Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Romiſh Creed endure the true Touch-Stone of the old Apoſtolical Faith: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conclude in a word; unleſs you are reſolv'd to chooſe ſuperſtitious Doctrin before Goſpel Truths; a falſe Religion before a true one; Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before Light, the <hi>Trent</hi> new Articles of-Faith, before the old Apoſtolical Creed, Never chuſe the Popiſh Religion before the Proteſtant.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
